A prefix sum pattern is one of those
which feels really easy in the
beginning. How hard can it be? You just
need to calculate a running total of all
of the elements.
But, as you start to solve these
problems, you will soon realize that it
can get very tricky.
The most difficult part is how do you
take advantage of the prefix sum that
you're calculating? How do you store it?
And how do you map it effectively so you
can make faster queries?
That is where the trick lies.
So, what we're going to do is we are
going to explore a variety of problems.
The underlying idea will always remain
the same. You have to maintain a prefix
sum. But, how do you use it? That is
where the magic is. So, without further
ado, let's get started.
First things first, what do you even
mean by a prefix sum? Well, the concept
is very, very simple. Let us say you are
given this particular array. And to
calculate the prefix sum, what do you do
is you start from the very beginning and
add up all of the elements one by one.
And you maintain this cumulative sum in
each of the indices.
So, what is going to happen is you are
going to maintain another array which
will have the exact same size.
Both of the arrays have seven elements.
And to find the prefix sum, you start
from the very beginning. What is the sum
currently? It is zero. The first element
is two.
So, you will write down a two here.
Then, 2 + 3 is 5. So, you write down a
five here.
Then you add the next element which is
five again, so you get a 10, then a 12,
then a seven, then a eight, and then a
12.
This is how you maintain your prefix
sum. And this array is often known as
the prefix sum array. This is used in a
lot of different places.
And that is it. This is all you need to
know how to build your prefix sum array.
This feels so simple, right? But, why
are its applications so very difficult?
Because you must need to understand how
can you apply them.
So, to get you warmed up, let us start
with the most basic problems that you
will find on the prefix sum concept.
This problem is often known as the range
sum query. Basically, you are given a
certain array and now you are given a
lot of different queries. You will be
given two indexes and you have to tell
me the sum of elements between these two
indexes. So, for example, I give you
this particular index and this
particular index.
You have to tell me the total sum.
It is fairly simple, right? You start
from five and then you add up all of the
elements until minus five.
So, what is the fuss?
Well, this array is very small.
You need to think that this array can be
huge and it can have 10,000 and lots of
elements.
Now,
I will give you a lot of queries one by
one. I will tell you, "Okay, tell me the
sum between first and the last element.
Tell me the sum between the middle
elements. Tell me the sum between the
third and the 10th element." It can be
any random query.
Now, if you iterate your array again and
again,
these queries will take up a lot of
time.
It is expected that you return me the
answer immediately. As soon as I ask
you, "Okay, tell me the answer in a
constant time." How do you do that? This
is where your prefix sum comes in handy.
So, first of all, what we do is we
maintain our prefix sum array.
Now, how is this helping me?
Try to think about it. Let us say I want
to find out the sum between this index
and this particular index.
I want to look the sum of these three
elements. Theoretically, what can I do
about it?
What if I take the sum of all of these
elements
and then if I subtract
the sum of all of these elements,
what am I remaining with?
I will be remaining with the sum of all
of these elements, correct?
So, do you see the concept of prefix sum
coming over here?
I am already maintaining a sum of all of
these elements. What is the sum? This
sum is eight.
And I am also maintaining a sum of all
of these elements. It is 10.
So, now if I have to find out the sum of
this middle sub array, what can I do?
I can take up eight
and then I can subtract 10 from it.
So, 8 - 10 will immediately give me -2.
Is -2 the answer? Yes, check it out. If
you add up all of these elements, 3 - 5
and that is -2.
So, what did you get? You were able to
perform your query in order of one time.
And notice, this particular concept can
work for any of the indices.
For example, if I want to find out the
sum between these two particular
indexes,
what do I need to do mathematically? I
will find out the sum of all of these
numbers. I have seven over here.
And then I have to subtract the sum of
all of these numbers, which I have two
over here. So, I can do 7 - 2 and that
gives me a five.
Is five the answer? Check it out. If you
add up all of these elements, you will
get five.
So, our concept works. And this is the
main idea how the concept of a prefix
sum works.
You find out all of the sum and then you
remove what was not needed.
This way, you will get something that
you need. This is the most basic problem
that involves the concept of a prefix
sum.
This was a one-dimensional array and you
were making all of those queries.
Now, there is a slight extension to this
problem and the problem is called range
sum query in two dimensions.
When you look at it for the first time,
it feels very very familiar. Instead of
a one-dimensional array, this time you
are given a two-dimensional array.
And remember, you were given two
indexes.
This time, you will be given two
particular points in your matrix.
And you have to find out the sum of all
of these numbers within this matrix.
So, the idea is same. You are given
certain numbers, and then you have to
find out the sum of a subsection.
But, how do you go about doing it? Where
do you even start? How do you start
forming your prefix sum over here?
Well, one thing is very, very sure. You
have to maintain some kind of an array
that stores your prefix sum.
And that is where you will start
building your prefix matrix.
This matrix is nothing but a equivalent
version of your prefix sum array.
So, this is a two-dimensional array.
But, how do you fill up all of the
values? Well, the first row and the
first column, they are very simple. You
can follow the same concept to populate
the first row, where you're adding all
of the numbers. So, three, then 3 + 0 is
3.
3 + 0 + 1 is 4.
3 + 0 + 1 + 4 is 8. And similarly, when
you add up all of these numbers, you get
a 10.
This way, you populated your first row.
What is this number telling you? This
number is telling you the sum of all of
these elements.
This number is telling you the sum of
all of these elements.
Similarly, you can populate your first
column, also. Just start adding all of
these numbers one by one. You get a
three.
3 + 5, you get an eight.
3 + 5 + 1, you get a nine. Then 9 + 4,
you get a 13.
And then, if you add up all of these
numbers, you will get a 14.
So, make sure what I'm doing over here.
Each of this number is telling me the
sum of all of these elements, right?
And this is what is very, very
important. You were able to populate
your first row and first column.
Now, think about it.
What should this number represent? We
are going to fill it in a while.
But, what it should represent?
It should represent the sum of all of
these elements. Correct?
Similarly, what should this number
represent? This number should represent
the sum of all of these elements.
This is how we are maintaining our 2D
prefix array. Correct?
Now, you have to actually fill it.
This particular number should have the
sum of all of these elements. Correct?
So, first of all, what numbers are we
adding? I know that six will be there
for sure. Correct?
And what other numbers? I will need to
have all of these three numbers also.
But, here is the fun part. Somehow, we
have already found out that sum.
What is the sum of these two numbers? It
is three.
And what is eight telling you? Eight is
telling you the sum of these two
numbers.
So, what do I have? I have the sum of
these two numbers.
I have the sum of these two numbers. And
I know about the number six.
But, notice. While calculating these two
sums, I counted this element twice.
So, I need to remove it in the first
time.
So, I will get a formula.
Prefix at I  J equals to matrix
at I  J
plus whatever is the top element because
I'm adding all of these two numbers plus
whatever is the left element because I'm
adding these two numbers. And then,
minus the top left because I added this
number twice. So, I remove three.
So, doing it all, I say six plus three
plus eight and minus three.
And that gives me 14.
So, I can safely write down 14 over
here.
What about the next number now?
For this particular number, it has to be
the sum of all of these elements.
Correct? So, first of all, I will take
the number that I already have, that is
three.
And then, what do I add? I add the top
number. So, top have all of these
elements. So, I get four.
Then I add the left number.
What is 14 calculating? 14 is
calculating all of these numbers.
And then notice, while adding all of
this, I calculated 3, 0 twice.
And what is the sum of 3, 0? It is this
particular number, that is top left. So,
I minus three.
Once you add up all of these, you will
get 14 + 4.
And that gives you a 18.
So, using this particular formula, you
can populate each member of this
particular matrix.
Once you have populated this entire
matrix, notice each element is telling
you the sum of all of these elements.
For example, 36. 36 means this is the
sum of all of these elements.
What is the sum of the entire matrix? It
will be 58.
So, I have solved at least one part. If
I'm given this particular point and any
other point in my matrix, I am able to
find out the sum.
Correct?
Now we need to solve for the part that
instead of the top left point, it could
be any other random point in my matrix.
I need to find out the sum of this
submatrix.
And this is the time we are going to use
our prefix array.
I would advise you here that you don't
complicate the concept. Just remember
the basics. What were we doing in one
dimension?
We calculated the sum up to the very
end.
And then removed what we did not need.
So, can we apply the same concept over
here?
I know that I want to find out the sum
of this particular matrix, right?
Where do I start? I can start at this
particular point, right?
So, if I look at 49,
49 is the sum of all of these elements,
correct?
And notice, I want to find out the sum
of a sub matrix within this.
So, whatever is the sum,
it will be 49 minus something. Correct?
Now, we need to figure out what we need
to subtract.
Check out this particular element.
This particular element calculates the
sum of this entire matrix.
And this is something that we do not
need.
So, I can say that I will remove 27 from
here.
What else can we remove?
Check out this particular element. This
particular element has the sum of this
entire matrix. Correct?
It means I need to remove 22 also.
But, is this the answer? No. Because
when we were removing this and when we
were removing this,
what just happened? We removed this
particular matrix twice.
It means I need to add it back again.
And what is the sum of this matrix? It
is given by this particular number,
right?
So, what I will need to do is I will
need to add back this particular matrix
only once.
So, I add this value.
And when I find out the sum, it will
give me a 14.
So, the sum of this particular sub
matrix,
it turns out to be 14. And this is your
answer.
So, once again, we took the concept of a
prefix sum array.
We applied the same base principle. Find
out the entire sum that you need and
then remove what is not needed.
Now, coming back to the basic question
of a one-dimensional array, you were
maintaining your prefix sum.
This problem can be asked in other
different ways also. For example, you
can be asked to find out the pivot
index.
Basically, a pivot index is a made-up
definition where the sum of elements on
the left is equal to the sum of elements
on the right.
Do you really feel it is a very
different problem?
All you need to do is find out the
cumulative sum from the left direction
and then find out the cumulative sum
from the right direction.
For any index, if the cumulative sum on
the left is equal to the cumulative sum
on the right, that's it. That is your
pivot index.
So, this is the starting point where a
prefix sum array starts to make sense
and you are able to take advantage out
of it.
Now, we can start to dive into the
tricky category and let us start with
the problem sub equals K.
Basically, you are given an array of
integers and a value K.
You have to tell me the total number of
sub arrays
whose sum equals K.
So, you can already see how tricky it
is.
And you have no idea that prefix sum can
even apply over here.
Look at the problem.
You have this particular array and you
are given the value of K equals to five.
You have to tell me all of the different
sub arrays, the count of all of these
sub arrays, such that the sum is five.
You can already see that, okay, 2 + 3,
this is five.
And then, if you add up all of these
elements,
once again, you will get the sum as
five.
If you add up all of these elements,
once again, the sum is five.
So, what is happening over here? How do
you even start? Certainly, a brute force
approach isn't the right solution over
here, correct?
Your very first hint that this problem
can involve a prefix sum is the fact
that you are interested in a sub array
with a certain sum.
And go back to your basics.
Why is a prefix sum helpful?
You want to find out the sum of a
certain sub array. What were you doing?
You found out the total sum and then you
removed what was not needed.
So, for example, I have this particular
array over here.
Now, notice. Let us say I have two
different indexes I and J.
Correct? I have maintained my prefix sum
array also.
So, what is the sum of this sub array?
If I look at this sub array, what is the
sum?
Can I say that the sum of this
particular sub array will be prefix sum
at J
so all of these elements minus prefix
sum at I minus 1.
So, I'm removing this particular section
from this entire section.
What I'm getting over here? This is the
sum of this particular sub array.
Correct?
This is the formula that I'm working
with.
And my value of K is 5.
So, is it safe to say that if this
particular difference is equal to K
then I have found out a valid sub array.
Right?
Because if this difference or if this
particular sum equals K, this is my sub
array. Correct?
All I am now remaining with is finding
out all of these different I and J
positions.
But even before that, we get a very
important formula that we can work with.
If I move around things a little bit I
can say that prefix sum at J minus K
equals to prefix sum at I minus 1.
What does that mean? It means that when
I am iterating through my array I'm
calculating the prefix sum. Correct?
And if I subtract this particular value
K
and then if I am able to find out a
value that I have already encountered
that means I have found out a valid sub
array.
So, what is this telling you? I can use
a hash map to store all of the prefix
sum that I have encountered so far. So,
while going ahead, I can look back and
check, "Hey, have I found out this sum
earlier?"
And at every iteration, I need to
subtract this value of K.
So, what are we doing here? I have my
array and I am maintaining a map of all
of the sums that I have seen so far.
We need to first initialize it.
I have seen a sum of zero once.
Because when I am not picking any
element, when I'm at the very first
location.
The sum is zero and I have seen it once,
correct?
This is your initial point where you
want to begin with.
Now you will try to iterate over your
array one by one.
You get the first element and that is
two.
So, the current sum is two.
And then what do you do? You try to see
two minus five, that is K.
Have you seen a minus three before?
No.
It means that this particular number
cannot form a valid sub array.
So, we can safely ignore it. But at the
same time, we need to update our map.
Basically, I found the sum of two and I
found it once, correct?
I move my pointer to the next location.
And then current sum is two plus three
and that is five.
And then I will check five minus K.
That is equal to zero.
Have I seen a zero before?
Check your map. Yes, and you saw a zero
once.
So, I can say that okay, I have found
out at least one sub array.
That is why I'm keeping a count.
And that is why you had to have a
starting point.
You had the prefix sum as zero over
here. And when you found a two elements,
you had the prefix sum as five. So, five
minus K and that is equal to zero.
That means you found your valid sub
array.
I update my total count to be one.
And then I also update my map saying
that I found a sum of five once.
I move on to my next element, that is
minus five. So, current sum is five my
plus of minus five and that is zero.
Zero minus five is equal to minus five.
Have I seen a minus five before? No, it
means no valid sub-arrays appear over
here.
But, I found a zero and I need to update
my map. Zero already exists in my map.
So, I will need to increment its count.
Why did we increment this? Because
notice, I found a sum of zero two times.
I found a sum of zero over here when I
did not have any numbers and I also
found a sum of zero over here when I had
all of these numbers.
And why is this important?
Because you are interested in finding
out all of the different sub-arrays. You
want the complete count. So, if I find
another number in the future that needs
a zero to complete the equation, then
you have found out two different
occurrences. That means you found out
two arrays. One will be the shorter
array and one will be the longer array.
That is why I'm maintaining a count.
So, up till now, my map has updated and
this is my current scenario.
Similarly, what you're going to do
you keep moving ahead and then you
encounter the next number. 0 + 5 = 5
and then 5 minus of K, that is 5, and
that is zero.
Have you found out a zero earlier? Yes,
and you found it two times.
So, I will take this two and I will add
it to my total count.
My total count has updated. It means up
till this point, I have found out three
different sub-arrays.
And does that check out?
This particular sub-array has a sum of
five. This particular sub-array,
although has a length of one, but has a
sum of five. And this entire particular
sub-array also has a sum of five.
So, up till this point, my conclusion is
valid and my method works correctly.
What I'm going to do next, I take up
this five and I increment the value in
my map.
This way, you will keep on proceeding
ahead for each of the element. You got a
minus five, so you will try to add it.
You got a zero and then you do a zero
minus five, and that gives you a minus
five. You don't have seen a minus five
earlier, so you will ignore it, but you
are going to update this value.
This way, you will keep on iterating up
to the very end, and this total count is
going to store that, okay, this is the
number of sub arrays that you have found
up till now.
Do you see how we are able to use the
prefix sum pattern? It is not intuitive
at first, but the dead giveaway is find
out a sub array with a particular sum.
And notice, this just works in a single
iteration. It does require a map to
store your prefix sum, but it is so
efficient.
And this particular problem is
notoriously famous for being asked in a
lot of different ways.
For example, over here, you were said
that, okay, the sum should be equal to
K.
It can be asked in so many different
ways.
It can ask you, okay, find out the sub
arrays with the sum of zero.
Do you think it is a different problem?
You just need to substitute K with zero,
and that is it.
Similarly, you can be asked, okay, find
out the sub arrays with equal number of
ones and zeros.
What is happening over here?
All you can do is substitute all of the
zeros with minus ones.
And then, once again, what do equal
number of zeros and ones mean? It means
that the sum of the sub array should be
equal to zero.
So, all of these are literally the same
problems. I have seen other variations
also, where you are said that, okay, the
sum should be the modulo of a particular
number.
Now, all of these things, they are
designed to confuse you.
But the underlying concept, it should
remain the same. So, make sure you burn
that concept in your mind.
If you are asked about a sub array sum
equaling K,
there is a very high chance that you
need to take the help of a prefix sum
array.
The trick lies in the part, how do you
recall the values that you have already
encountered?
Based upon a very similar concept, let
us look at one more problem that
involves the prefix sum pattern.
This is known as the longest subarray
sum equals K.
So, up till now, we were just counting
the number of subarrays.
This time, I want to find out the
longest subarray out of all of those
subarrays such that the sum equals K.
So, once again, you are given an array
of integers
and you are given a value K.
Now, you have to tell me what is the
longest subarray that the sum is K.
For example, if you notice, this is a
subarray with just a single element. Its
sum is four.
This is a even bigger subarray. Its
length is four and its sum is also four.
This is a shorter subarray with a sum of
four but length of two.
So, in this case, what will be your
answer?
This array will be your answer.
You can easily see that how this problem
can be tricky.
If you start adding negative numbers to
it, once again, the opportunities and
the boundaries can increase.
You can have a even bigger subarray.
So, how do you go about it?
Let us recall the idea of the prefix sum
that we had.
For example, if I have this particular
array and I have two positions I and J.
The value of K is four, correct?
So, what is the prefix sum until this
particular position?
Until the position I, the prefix sum is
14, correct?
And what is the prefix sum until
position J? If you add up all of these
elements, you get the sum of 18.
How do you find out this particular sum?
What we did is we subtracted this
difference. Prefix sum at J minus prefix
sum at I.
You are remaining with a certain
subarray.
And if this value is equal to K,
then this is a valid subarray, correct?
So, let us establish some of the similar
groundwork. We have an array and I have
maintained a map. Earlier, I was keeping
a map of the sum and the count.
This time, I'm interested in a longest
subarray.
So instead of the count, I'm going to
maintain that, okay, what is the first
occurrence of the sum that I
particularly saw?
Notice that if I see zero multiple
times,
then I want the longest subarray.
We were counting it twice, but this
time, I'm interested in the first
position where I found the sum zero. So
I will be looking at a longer array.
And now, what we're going to do is we
are going to apply exactly the same
concept. You start from the very first
position.
You have the sum as five.
So 5 - 4
is one.
And have you seen one in your array? No.
So what I'm going to do is I will take
up this five and I will add it in my
array.
I add the sum as five and what position
did I see it at? I saw it at the
position zero.
And now what do you do? Simply take your
pointer and move it to the next
location.
You add up the number. Prefix sum is 5 +
2 and that is seven.
7 - 4 is three.
Have you seen a three earlier? No. So I
will add seven and I will say one.
It means that I saw a sum of seven at
the position one.
Move to the next location.
The next number is two.
So I get a nine. 9 - 4
that is five.
Now you check, have you seen a five
earlier? You saw a five at the zeroth
index.
It means that you have found out a valid
subarray.
And what is its length? Its length will
be the current index minus when you
first saw it.
So 2 - 0 and that is a two.
So I'm maintaining a variable result
max. It means the maximum subarray I
have seen so far.
So, I store a two in here.
Now you're getting the idea, right?
Similarly, what you can do is you can
move on to the next element.
9 + 5 is 14.
14 - 4 is 10.
Have you seen a 10 earlier? No, but you
need to add 14 to your sum.
This way, you will continue on for every
index, and you will notice that when
your pointer moves over here,
you will find the sum to be 18, and you
will find the sum to be 14 over here.
18 - 14 gives you a four,
and you will compare. Have you found out
a bigger sub array? Yes. So, you're
going to update this two to four
because that is what you want. You want
to find out all of the different sub
arrays and keep a track of the longest
that you have found till now.
And once again, this is how prefix sum
comes to your rescue. We just did a
single iteration of the array, and we
have a very efficient solution.
Now, these are some of the problems
where a prefix sum pattern actually
comes in very, very handy.
I hope this is now giving you a very
good idea where you can start to apply
the prefix sum.
As soon as you see that, okay, I need a
sub array with a particular sum.
Especially if it's an integer array.
This is where a prefix sum concept can
come very, very handy.
So, when going through all the video,
did you face any problems? And what
other problems have you found out that
involves the prefix sum pattern?
Tell me everything in the comment
section below, and it will become a very
good place for all of the discussion. I
will be happy to understand all of these
problems, and I can solve all of these
doubts as well.
And if you're liking all of this type of
content, please do consider subscribing
to my channel and share this video with
your friends. This really keeps me
motivated, and I can make more such
videos.
Also, a huge shout-out to all of the
members who support my channel. You guys
really keep me going. And as a member,
you do get priority reply to your
comments and early access to new videos
as well.
Also, remember that now you can schedule
one-to-one sessions with me and we can
discuss about almost anything.
Stay tuned for my upcoming video. Until
then, see ya.